Guide to the Ervin K. Zingler papers, 1936-1989 MS 435
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Ervin K. Zingler papers
1936-1989
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Zingler, Ervin K.
MS 435
2 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
These papers include correspondence between University of Houston economist Ervin Zingler and his wife, Gilberta, as well as academic materials, publications and awards.
Biographical / Historical
Economist Ervin K. Zingler was born in Wisconsin in 1913. He graduated B.A., Summa Cum Laude, from Lawrence University in 1935, M.A. University of Illinois 1936, Ph. D. University of Illinois 1938. He taught in many schools, including University of Cape Town, South Africa, University of Wisconsin, Vanderbilt University, New York University, University of Illinois and University of Houston. He also served in the government as Chief Economist, 1944-1953.
Zingler was posthumously honored by a professorship being named for him at Rice University, known as the Ervin K. Zingler Professor of Economics and Professor of Management, Jones Graduate School of Management, Rice University. The Zingler Chair was established by Gilberta Zingler, former assistant librarian for resources at Rice's Fondren Library, to honor her late husband, who was a professor of economics at the University of Houston. In Spring 1988, the Rice Board of Governors approved the appointment of Malcolm Gillis as the first Ervin Kenneth Zingler Professor of Economics.
Scope and Contents
These papers include correspondence between economist Ervin Zingler and his wife, Gilberta, as well as academic materials, publications and awards.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Gilberta Zingler,1993.
Index Terms
Subjects
Economics; Education
- Series I: Correspondence, 1946-1986; 46819
  - Ervin to Gilberta, Texas 1946-1955, 46822 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ervin to Gilberta, Washington, DC 1948-1950, 46823 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ervin to Gilberta, Arkansas 1949, 46824 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ervin to Gilberta, Louisiana 1949, 46825 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ervin to Gilberta, Chicago 1950, 46826 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ervin to Gilberta, Oklahoma 1950-1953, 46827 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ervin to Gilberta, California 1955, 46828 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ervin to Gilberta, University of Colorado 1958, 46829 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ervin to Gilberta, Vanderbilt University 1960, 46830 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ervin to Gilberta, University of Puerto Rico 1963, 46831 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ervin to Gilberta, Farleigh Dickinson University 1964, Teaneck, NJ, 46832 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ervin to Gilberta, University of Arizona 1966, 46833 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ervin to Gilberta, University of Wyoming 1967, 46834 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ervin to Gilberta, University of Nebraska 1968, 46835 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Condolence cards and letters 1989-1990, 46836 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Zingler Scholarship 1990, 46837 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous 1949-1986, 46838 (Box 1, Envelope 17)
- Series II: Personal and Academic Materials, 1913-1990; 46820
  - Birth Certificate, 1913, 46839 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Education, 46840 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Thesis 1936 "Theoretical Aspects of the Laws of Cost" University of Illinois, 46841 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Vitae, 46842 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Omicron Delta Epsilon, 46843 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Death certificate and obituary 1989, 46844 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Resolutions and memorials honoring E.K. Zingler 1990, 46845 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Faculty notices/ announcements/ lectures, University of Houston 1953- 1985, 46846 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Notices/ announcements, 46847 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Research / reference materials, 46848 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Course materials, Folder 1 of 2, 46849 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Course materials, Folder 2 of 2, 46850 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Assorted printed materials, 46851 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Clippings, 46852 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Photographs, 46853 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Series III: Publications and Awards, 1957-1979 and undated; 46821
  - "The Proposed Value Added Tax for USA", 46854 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Parts of unpublished book by EKZ, 46855 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - St. Mary's University Graduate School, publications, published articles, 46856 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - University of Houston publications, published articles, 46857 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Publications, Folder 1 of 2: The Determination of Economic Feasiblility of Multiple-Purpose Dams, April 1957; Economic Feasiblity of Multi-Purpose Dams; Economic Feasibility Study for the Community Bank; Economic Feasibility Study for the Northgate State Bank The Post Oak National Bank, 46858 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Publications, Folder 2 of 2: Advertising and the Maximisation of Profit and reprint; "Veblen vs. Commons: A Comparative Evaluation" reprints; "Land-Value Taxation and Contemporary Economic Thought"; "The National Labor Relations Board and the Federal Courts" The Executive, "The Folklore of Administered Prices"; Review of Problems of Economic Policy, 46859 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Awards: Omicron Delta Epsilon award for Outstanding Service to the Society, 1979; Omicron Delta Epsilon Distinguished Award for Outstanding Service to the Society, 1971; University of Houston Emeriti Award, 1979; University of Houston Men's Club pins: 3-20 years, 46860 (Box 4, Folder 39)